<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of enquirie to be ministred concerning the Admiraltie in the county of Sussex. Anno Dom. 1638</title>
            <author>England and Wales. High Court of Admiralty.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23444</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102436</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838221</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838221</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2588</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2588)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1085:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles of enquirie to be ministred concerning the Admiraltie in the county of Sussex. Anno Dom. 1638</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. High Court of Admiralty.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B[ernard] A[lsop] for for Richard Meighen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Articles concerning the Admiraltie.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi]¹ A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Cropped at head, affecting running title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sussex (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2588:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES OF ENQVIRIE TO BE MINISTRED CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Admiraltie</hi> in the County of SUSSEX.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1638.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>B. A.</hi> for for RICHARD MEIGNEN. 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:2588:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2588:2"/>
            <head>Articles of Enquirie to be miniſtred con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Admiraltie</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex.</hi> ANNO DOM. 1638.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nprimis,</hi> you ſhall truly preſent without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of perſons, all ſuch as haue any time within theſe Twelue yeares laſt, propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Sundayes in going out to take Fiſh by themſelues or their ſeruants.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> you ſhall preſent all Pirates, Robbers, Murderers, Felons and théeues, that haue committed any Piracy, Robbery, Murder or Felony vpon the high Seas, or within any Freſh-water, Haven, River or tréeke from all Bridges next vnto the Sea within full Sea marke, or on the Sea ſands within the Iuriſdiction of the Admiralty in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> againſt any of the Kings Majeſties Subjects or any other his friends or Allies, and of their Receiuers, Counſellers, Ayders or Abetters, procurers, comforters or maintainers, either by words, vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals, Ships, Boates, Artillery, Weapon, Gunne, powder, or any other thing, and the Receiuers of their ſpoyles and buyers of Pirates goods.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Item,</hi> yée ſhall inquire and true preſentment make, of all petty Pickers, petty Felons, and private Théeues, that breaketh any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, fardels, packes, Dry-fats, cheſts or other like, vpon board any Ship or other veſſell, or that ſtealeth Oares, Anchors, apparell, tackle of any Ship or Boate, or any Fiſhermens nets, hookes, pots, Fiſh or other things.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Item,</hi> yée ſhall inquire and true preſentment make, of all thoſe that haue taken any Ships, veſſels, goods, or Priſoners vpon the Sea, or elſe-where, for any matter done vpon the Sea, or any other River, freſh-water, or créeke within the Kings Majeſties juriſdiction of his Highneſſe ſaid Admiralty in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and haue not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the ſame in this Court accordingly.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb facs="tcp:2588:3"/>5 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall truly inquire and true preſentment make of the ſlaughter of men, done and made by any Ship, veſſell, or boate, or any apparell of them. And of all dead bodies found that haue come to their deaths vpon the Sea, or in any other Haven, Riuer, Freſhwater, or Créeke, within the Iuriſdiction of the Admiralty aforeſaid, which haue not beene preſented in this Court (as it apperteyneth) or that haue had any Gold, Silver, Iewels, or other things found vpon them, and the like preſentment hath not béene made thereof.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire, and true preſentment make of all Riots, vnlawfull aſſemblyes, contempts, Concealments, routs, treſpaſſes, frayes, out-cryes, blood-ſheds, maymes, quarrels, menacings, or threatnings, Weapons-drawing, or any other act, crime, or treſpaſſe, done and committed againſt the Kings peace, and Lawes of this Realme, vpon the Sea, or vpon any other Haven, Port, place, Riuer, Freſh-water or Créeke, within full Sea marke, or on the Seaſands, or elſe where from the firſt Bridge next vnto the Sea within the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Admiraltie in the county of <hi>Suſſex</hi> in any Ship, veſſell, or Boate, or vpon the Sea ſands within the foreſaid Iuriſdiction, and true preſentment make of the offenders, their names and dwelling places.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire and true preſentment make of all them that haue laden or doe vſe to lade any goods or merchandize, either vpon the high Sea, or in any Hauen, Freſh-water, Riuer or Créeke, within the Iuriſdiction of the Admiraltie in the county of <hi>Suſſex</hi> in or vpon any ſtrange Bottome, either within this Realme or without, where they might haue had Engliſh Ships to ſerue them, according to the Lawes of the Realme.</p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire and true preſentment make of all them that haue ſhipped, or laden any Ship, Veſſell, or Boate, lying vpon the high Sea, or in any other Hauen, Freſh-water, Riuer, or Créeke, from the firſt Bridge next vnto the Sea, within the Iuriſdiction of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltie in the county of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> with Wheat, Rye, Barley, Oates, Mault or any other Grayne, and haue tranſported the ſame beyond the Seas contrary to the Lawes of this Realme. And ye ſhall truely declare the names of the Merchants, owners and maſters of ſuch Corne and Ships with the names of the ſame Ships.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall truely preſent, all them that haue laden, ſhipped, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, carryed, ſold, or conveyed any Wheat, Rye, Barley, Beanes, Mault, or any other Corne, Tallow, Leather, Braſſe, Lead, Candles,
<pb facs="tcp:2588:3"/> Chéeſe, Butter, or other Victualls, in any Ship, Veſſell, or Boate, out of the Realme into any other Realmes, from any Freſh-water, Riuer, Créeke, or place, within the Iuriſdiction of the Admiraltie in the foreſaid county of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> contrary to the Lawes and cuſtomes of this Realme, whereby his Majeſtie hath béene deceiued, and not paid his juſt cuſtomes and Subſidy, and the common wealth hurted.</p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall truly inquire, and true preſentment make of all them that either by day or night, lade any Ships or Veſſels in ſecret Créeks or places (being no common or open Port) or that doe helpe to convey and leade ſtrangers Ships into any ſuch priuate Créeke or place, whereby the ſecret Landing places on the Seacoaſts may bée knowne to ſtrangers.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall preſent all Fiſhmongers and all other perſons, that bée fore-ſtallers or regraters or kéepers of Markets vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or the ſhores within the Iuriſdiction of the Admiraltie in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> whereby the common wealth and the Markets bée abuſed, (That is to ſay) all them that foreſtall, regrate and buy any manner of goods, merchandize, or Victualls vpon the water or ſhore as aforeſaid, before it come to the place, or Port where it is to be diſcharged and ſold.</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire and truly preſent all that cut or let ſlip any Boy, or Boyes-rope whereby any Anchor is loſt, or cut any Cable, or any Tackling of Ship, Veſſell, or Boat, in any Hauen, Riuer, or Port, from all Bridges next vnto the Sea within the Iuriſdiction of the Admiraltie in the county of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> whereby the Ship or Veſſell driueth, or otherwiſe is in perill of hurt taking, or any man thereby in perill of life.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire of all that ſend vnlawfull Anchors, Cable or Tacklings, in any Ship or other Veſſell to the Sea, whereby the ſame might ſtand in danger to bée caſt away, and the Marriners in perill of their liues,</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire and truly preſent all manner of vnlawfull Nets, or other Engines vſed by Fiſhermen, where with any manner or kind of Fiſh or fry of Fiſh is deſtroyed, to the hurt of the common wealth.</p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire and truly preſent all thoſe that haue drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged any Oyſters or Muſcles or put them to ſayle at vnſeaſonable times (that is to ſay) At times prohibited by the Lawes and cuſtomes of the Admiraltie, all thoſe that doe any hurt or annoyance to the Beds
<pb facs="tcp:2588:4"/> and Brood of Oyſters and Muſcles; And alſo thoſe that haue taken in ſeuered and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngroſſed any Oyſter plots or Beds for their private profit.</p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Item</hi> ye ſhall inquire and preſent all them that haue carryed any Gold or Siluer Bullion, or Plate in any Ship into any other Realme.</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire and preſent all them that haue found any Ship, Veſſell, or Boat waffing on the high Seas or in any Freſh water Riuer or Créeke, within the Iuriſdiction of the Admiraltie in the county of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> without Owner, and haue not preſented the ſame to this Court.</p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire and truely preſent all thoſe that haue found vpon the Sea, or any other Riuer, Hauen, Freſhwater or Créeke, or elſe where by the Sea-ſide, within the Iuriſdiction of the Admiralty in the county of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> any Flotzon: as Tonne, Pipe, Oyle, Wine, Bale, Truſts, Maſts, Sayles, Yards, Timber, or any other manner of thing whatſoeuer it were, and haue not preſented the ſame and them that ſuch things poſſeſſe.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire and truely preſent all men that haue found in the bottome of the Sea, or in any other Hauen, Freſh water, Riuer, or Créeke, within the foreſaid Iuriſdiction any Lagon, as Anchors, Gunnes, Yron, Stéele, Tynne, Lead, or other mettall or things, Gold or Silver, and haue not juſtly preſented the ſame to this Court.</p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire and duly preſent, all them that haue main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vpon the high Streame of any Ports, Hauens, or Créeks, within the foreſaid Iuriſdicton, any Mills, Weares, Kidles, and ſtakes or other things, to the annoyance of the navy of this Realme, or hurt of any channell or Streame, or that caſteth any Ballaſt or other things into the ſame.</p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall inquire of them that haue taken any Fiſh Royall, or other Fiſh accuſtomed to the Kings Maieſtie and the Office of his high Admiraltie of <hi>England</hi> (That is to ſay) Whales, Ballens, Sturgeons, Grapes, Dolphin, Porpoſe or any Fiſh that is of great growth, or taken or r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>puted for a Fiſh Royall, and haue not preſented (as it apperteyneth accordingly.)</p>
            <p n="22">22 <hi>Item,</hi> ye ſhall diligently inquire and true preſentment make of all ſuch Mariners, Saylers, Fiſhermen, and all other Watermen which haue at any time before this abſented and withdrawne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from any of his Maieſties Preſts or at any other time from the ſervice for the Realme to ſerve in his highneſſe Nauy, and haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come reteyned ſeruants with any man for that time, or haue receiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2588:4"/> Preſt money, and ſo haue gone their wayes: name all ſuch perſons.</p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Item,</hi> yée ſhall preſent all idle Mariners, Saylers, Wherrimen, Tiltboat-men, Fiſhermen, and Bargemen, that vſe any loytering, playing at Dice and cards, and haunt Ale-houſes, and Tavernes with idle company, and doe not continually follow and giue themſelues to their Occupations, nor are content to ſerue in Covenant for any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable wages: All ſuch you ſhall by name ſpecifie and declare.</p>
            <p n="24">24 <hi>Item,</hi> yée ſhall preſent all thoſe perſons that haue made any Frayes, or drawne any Blood in or vpon any ſhip, Veſſell, Barge, Boate, or elſe-where within full Sea marke, (within the foreſaid Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Admiraltie) or in any wiſe breaketh the Kings peace, and be common pickers of Quarrels: Name all ſuch with their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling places?</p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>Item</hi> yée ſhall preſent all thoſe perſons, which haue throwne any Dung, chaulke, rubbiſh, or noyſome thing into the Sea or any ſea paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, to the hurt of the ſame, within the foreſaid Iuriſdiction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Name the offenders therein?</p>
            <p n="26">26 <hi>Item</hi> yee ſhall preſent all thoſe, that haue caſt any Anchor into the Sea, or River without a Boy or marke vpon the ſame, whereby danger hath or might enſue to any Ship, Veſſell, Barge, Boate, or mans body?</p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Item</hi> yée ſhall preſent all Handicrafts men, and other perſons, that haue vſed and exerciſed this yeare paſt, or at any time before, any Nets, or other Engines to take Oyſters, or other Fiſh, and haue not béene Apprentice to the craft of Fiſhing?</p>
            <p n="28">28 <hi>Item</hi> ye ſhall preſent all thoſe that take any to ſeruice in the craft or ſcience of Fiſhing, but for terme of yéeres whereby they may haue their preſent knowledge and learning in the Water-craft and trade of Fiſhing.</p>
            <p n="29">29 <hi>Item</hi> ye ſhall preſent all thoſe that haue v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xed, troubled, arreſted or impriſoned a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Mariner, Seaman, Fiſhermen, or other perſons, for any contract, bargaine, treſpaſſe, hurt or other thing done vpon the Sea in any Hauen, Freſh water, Riuer or Creeke, within the Iuriſdiction of the Kings Maieſties ſaid Court of the Admiraltie in the county of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> in any other court or place, in contempt of the Kings Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Admiraltie aforeſaid. Enquire diligently for this and ſpecifie their names, ſirnames, and dwelling places?</p>
            <p n="30">30 <hi>Item,</hi> yée ſhall inquire diligently, and make true preſentment of all ſuch cuſtomes, orders, and vſages, as haue formerly béene obſerued
<pb facs="tcp:2588:5"/> in the Townſhip, Villages, and places, in which you now ſeuerally dwell, touching the taking of Cockles, and all thoſe that haue broken any of the ſaid cuſtomes or Orders within theſe Twelue yéeres laſt paſt.</p>
            <p n="31">31 <hi>Item,</hi> yée ſhall preſent all thoſe that haue priuately ſold at the waters ſide, or elſewhere, or carryed to Market in Bags, or that ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth abroad in the countreyes, any ſmall broode or fry of Fiſh not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketable, or that haue taken any Fiſh before the acuſtomed time of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof, to the great deſtruction of the increaſe of the Fiſh. Name the offenders in this point.</p>
            <p n="32">32 <hi>Item,</hi> yée ſhall diligently inquire and truely preſent, whether any Kidles, Stanks, Stakes, or Weares, haue bin or bée newly erected, builded vſed, and occupyed in any Creeke, Port, Hauen, or other place vnto the ſame adioyning within the Kings Iuriſdiction of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltie in the county of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ex</hi> aforeſaid, whereof let true preſentment bée made, declaring in what places, and by whom the ſame were or are ſo builded, made or vſed, how many there bée in number: who be their owners, and what kind of young fry of Fiſh they doe commonly vſe to deſtroy, and when the time is to begin to fiſh, and to leaue of by anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cuſtome.</p>
            <p n="33">33 <hi>Item,</hi> yée ſhall preſent the maiſh of the vnlawfull Nettes and other vnlawfull Engines, vſed and occupyed in the ſaid Kidles and Weares.</p>
            <p n="34">34 <hi>Item,</hi> yée ſhall preſent all other ancient cuſtomes, Orders, and vſages vſed and frequented in fiſhing trade amongſt the old Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Townſhips, Villages, and places, in which you doe now ſeuerally dwell, as well of the times and ſeaſons accuſtomed to Fiſh, the names and Aſſizes of your Nets, as what kinde and ſort of Fiſh are commonly taken by your labour from time to time.</p>
            <p n="35">35 <hi>Item,</hi> you ſhall inquire diligently and make true preſentment of all ſuch Fiſhermen, as haue taken, ſold, or brought to Markets in the high Sea, or in any Haven, Freſh water, Riuer, or Créeke within the Kings Iuriſdiction of his Admiraltie, within the county of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the loweſt Bridges next to the Sea, any Bace, Mullets, Soales, Plaice, Flounders, Turbuts, or other Fiſh of a leſſe aſſize, or ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, then by your ancient cuſtomes, vſages, or the law is allowed.</p>
            <p n="36">36 <hi>Item,</hi> you ſhall preſent all Podders that come to ſecret places on the Seacoaſt, and there regrate the Fiſh whereby the common Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets are defrauded.</p>
            <p n="37">
               <pb facs="tcp:2588:5"/>37 <hi>Item,</hi> you ſhall preſent all Fiſhermen that doe ſell their Fiſh at ſuch ſecret places of the Sea coaſts, where no priuate Markets ought to bée.</p>
            <p n="38">38 <hi>Item,</hi> you ſhall preſent all Cable-hangers, That is to ſay, Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Shoemakers, or Handicrafts-men, being not brought vp in Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Science, that doe goe, or ſend any of their Seruants to the Sea, whereby Mariners and Fiſhermen or their ſcience ſhould in any wiſe decay, or be hindered.</p>
            <p n="39">39 <hi>Item,</hi> you ſhall preſent all ſea men, that doe ſend any young men, or Lads either to fiſhing or ſayling in any veſſell or boate, except there be a ſufficient number of able men therein, to guide the ſame without perill of drowning, or caſting away for lacke of government.</p>
            <p n="40">40 <hi>Item,</hi> you ſhall preſent all nuſances committed or done vpon the Sea ſhore, or vpon the ſhore of any Hauen or Créeke below high wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter markes, whereby the ſhore is any way impayred, or annoyed, or the liberty of the paſſage hindered.</p>
            <p n="41">41 <hi>Item,</hi> you ſhall preſent all other annoyances, Crimes, evill facts, diſorders or hurts, which are in any wiſe preiudiciall or hurtfull, aſwell to poore Fiſhermens and Sea-fayring mens liues, or to the common wealth or Nauy of this Realme.</p>
            <p n="42">42 Of theſe and all other offences, hurts and annoyances vſed committed or done in any reſpect vpon the Sea, or in any Riuer or Créeke belonging to the ſame within the Iuriſdiction of his Maieſties Admiraltie in the county of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> for the ſpace of Twelue yéeres laſt paſt, you are diligently to inquire and true preſentment make, vpon the Oathes of euery of you, and the ſame to giue vp in writing vnder your hands.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
